Frank Bené papers, 1905-1943
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Frank Bené papers, 1905-1943
MS 386
Bené, Frank, 1905-1943
This collection consists chiefly of photographs, published works, and research materials related to or collected by Frank Bené regarding his observations and writings on hummingbirds in Arizona. The collection also includes professional and biographical materials as well as correspondence.
1 linear foot
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Frank Bené was born June 11, 1905 in Isaszeg, Hungary and came to the U.S. just over a year later. His family settled in Bethlehem, Pennsylvania where Bené attended grade school and high school. After spending some time out west, he returned to Pennsylvania and graduated with honors from Lehigh University in 1933, and eventually received a Masters degree in Education from the same institution. In June 1933, he was married to Katharine Johnson. Bené worked as an instructor in social studies in the Adult Evening School in Bethlehem for one year and in 1935 was named county supervisor of Americanization in charge of literacy and citizenship for foreign-born residents of Northampton County. For the following four years he taught, published, and worked in the field of citizenship training while pursing his interest in adult education.
As a result of failing health, Frank Bené moved to Phoenix, Arizona in 1937. It was at this time that a serious interest in ornithology began. Over the next five years, he read, investigated, and wrote a number of articles, particularly short papers for The Condor (1940, 1941, 1945) along with the memoir entitled The Feeding and Related Behavior of Hummingbirds, which won the Walker Prize of the Boston Society of Natural History in 1942.
An improvement in health permitted Frank to teach science for a year in New Jersey. In January, 1943, he returned to Arizona and took a faculty position at Arizona State Teachers College in Tempe, instructing U.S. Army cadets at the Pre-Flight School. However, the inadequately diagnosed tubercular illness Frank suffered from became increasingly acute and he resigned his position in October and died in Phoenix on December 18, 1943.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series.
Series I: Biographical, 1923-1943
Series II: Correspondence, 1943-1956
Series III: Published Writings, 1939-1945
Series IV: Collected Writings, 1905-1946
Series V: Photographs, 1939-1943
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists chiefly of biographical materials, photographs, published works, and research materials relating to observations and writings on hummingbirds in Arizona.
The collection includes a box of envelopes of photographs and negatives of hummingbirds. The envelopes are dated and include descriptions of photographs that are not always consistent with the contents. Bené named several of the hummingbirds he studied (Battlescar, Long-neck, and Sally) and these names appear in some of the descriptions.
Access Terms
Bené, Frank, 1905-1943.
Ornithology.
Hummingbirds -- Arizona.
Birds -- Arizona.
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 1923-1943
  - Photographs-Frank Bené Katherine Bené (?), March 3, 1939; unknown (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diploma, Bethlehem High School, June 21, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lehigh Commencement program, June 13, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diploma, Lehigh University, B.A., June 13, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Contract for teaching position at Lehigh University, September 3, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diploma, Lehigh University, M.A., October 5, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Description of the Walker Prize in Natural History, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lehigh University Teacher's Credentials document, April, 8, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dayton News, November 23, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Official transcripts, Lehigh University, January 8, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter of recommendation from L.Tennent Lee Jr., July 24, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper article on Walker Prize, October 16, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper article on Walker Prize, November 12, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Excerpts from letters of recommendation, No date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Obituary, December 20, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1943-1956
  - Margaret Baker to Frank Bené, August 26, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amy Tuttle (?) to Kitty and Frank Bené, September 27, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Warren W. Halsey to Frank Bené, September 27, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Baker to Frank Bené, October 27, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harold P. Thomas to Frank Bené, November 12, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harry V. Bené to Frank Bené, November 24, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thank you card, No date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sympathy card from Frank Drigiani, No date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Horace D. Hontz to Mrs. C. Bené, December 22, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alden H. Miller to Katherine Johnson Bené, February 11, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Baker to Mrs. Frank Bené, February 15, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Baker to Mrs. Frank Bené, August 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Baker to Mrs. Frank Bené, December 13, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Frank Bené to Miss Margaret Baker, January 17, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Martha Morrow to Frank Bené, February 27, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alden H. Miller to Martha Morrow, March 23, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - M.J.R. Morris to Frank Bené, June 21, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hilda W. Grinnell to Mrs. Frank Bené, December 9, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Martha Morrow to Mrs. Wallace Haverty, December 17, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hilda W. Grinnell to Mrs. Haverty, December 23, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David L. Garrison to Mrs. Wallace Haverty, May 23, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David L. Garrison to Mrs. Wallace Haverty, June 12, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David L. Garrison to Mrs. Wallace Haverty, July 10, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dora (?) to Kitty, December 22, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christina Lopes to Mrs. W. G. Haverty, June 7, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert J. Niedrach to Mrs. Wallace G. Haverty, May 1, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harold E. Edgerton to Mr. and Mrs. Wallace G. Haverty, August 2, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harold E. Edgerton to Mrs. Wallace G. Haverty, March 5, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alice Atkinson to Mrs. Wallace, [July 7, 1952] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lovie M. Whitaker to Mr. Bené, May 6, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Bleitz to Mrs. Haverty, March 24, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Bleitz to Mrs. Haverty, June 18, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Bleitz to Mrs. Haverty, September 2, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jean and Peter O'Blevis (?) to Mr. and Mrs. Haverty, April 26, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Bleitz to Mrs. Haverty, May 31, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Bleitz to Mrs. Haverty, June 16, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Crawford H. Greenewalt to Mrs. Wallace G. Haverty, May 29, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jean and Peter O'Blevis (?) to Mr. and Mrs. Haverty, No date (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III: Published Writings, 1939-1945
  - The Condor, July-August, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Condor, September-October, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Condor, November-December, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Condor, January-February, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - People's Magazine of Arizona (photocopy), July, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - People's Magazine of Arizona, October, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - People's Magazine of Arizona, November, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Desert Magazine, October, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Science New Letter, June 9, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Feeding and Related Behavior of Hummingbirds, by Frank Bené, no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Collected Writings, 1905-1946
  - Black and white illustrations of birds, No dates (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Misc. magazine pages, No dates (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Misc. photocopies of articles, photos, etc., No dates (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Zoological Quarterly Bulletin, May 15, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National League for Woman's Service Magazine, January, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bené: The Hummingbird Man, by Mary Estes, No date (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series V: Photographs, 1939-1943
  - 6 envelopes of hummingbird bird photographs and negatives, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 15 envelopes of hummingbird photographs and negatives, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 9 envelopes of hummingbird photographs and negatives, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2 envelopes of hummingbird photographs and negatives, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 3 envelopes of hummingbird photographs and negatives, 1939-1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Misc. photographs of Arizona landscapes, plants, birds, No dates (Box 2, Folder 6)